[Music]
So, without further ado, we're playing
15 + 10. We're playing longer games. We
are putting an accent on the openings.
And uh let's hope for a a somewhat more
competitive game. Here we go.
Okay, we're playing thousand.
And I remind you that my sort of
official recommendation in this speedrun
is the accelerated dragon, which is
actually the opening that I started
with, our very first speedrun. I was
almost exclusively playing the
accelerated. We had great results and
it's an incredibly easy tolearn weapon
that I recommend to a wide variety of
players. C4. So C4 is already a pretty
big surprise. It's a move. So, I've I've
seen this move before and it's not it's
not a terrible move. You can almost
think of this as a transposition to an
English, right? White can also play C4.
You can respond with C5 and then white
can play E4 and move two. Now, the the
obvious drawback of this move, and this
is really the first thing that should
jump out at you, is of course the fact
that white has created this massive hole
on D4. And a hole is the definition of a
hole or a weakness is a square that
cannot hypothetically even be defended
by any pawns. And often that's because
the pawns which could defend the square
are now one step further. In this case,
the E and the C pawns have advanced to
the fourth rank. They cannot themselves
defend a square on the fourth rank. So,
of course, this gives the knight
potentially a massive outpost on D4. But
what a lot of people don't understand is
that just because the hole exists
doesn't mean that you want to occupy it
ASAP. We should start with the move
knight C6, but not because we're going
to play knight D4 on the next move. It's
it's way too early to occupy the outpost
because we don't have any other pieces
developed. And if we put a knight on d4
straight away, then white's just going
to go knight f3 and knock our knight off
of d4. It's more the long-term weakness
that's going to cost white later on down
the line when all of the development is
complete. But the other thing that we
get is we get a potentially massive
diagonal for our dark squareed bishop.
Knight f3.
So here there's kind of a really
interesting moment. The move that we are
going to play is G6.
But if I were playing a classical game,
you know, a real over the board game,
and somebody played this against me, I
actually would play a somewhat different
move. I would play the move E6 or knight
F6. And after the game, I'll talk a
little bit about why. But the basics of
why should be clear to you. What does
the move G6 allow white to do? Should
white want to transition to main lines?
What is the drawback of the move g6
here? Yeah, of course it allows white to
push the pawn to d4. And after d4, c
takes d4, knight takes d4, we transpose,
and we're going to play g6 directly to
the marotzi bind variation of the
accelerated dragon. But since we're
putting the emphasis on openings, I
actually wouldn't mind that. But from a
purely objective standpoint, the way to
quote unquote punish white for playing
C4 is of course not to allow a
transposition to main lines. It's to put
pressure on the E4 pawn, try to prevent
white from playing D4 in a good version.
But hopefully my logic makes sense. And
our opponent has played D3. Um, and that
that solidifies the hole on D4. And
after bishop G7, we're flat out better
out of the opening. We've got great
pieces and we we're dominating the dark
squares in the center. And of course,
not not to mention the fact that white's
bishop, light squareed bishop is now
essentially a big pawn. So hopefully
we'll get some erotis a little bit
later. Knight c3. And now we can
continue our development in rather
normal fashion. So in general in such
positions, it's uh a self-evidently good
idea to trade our light squareed bishop
for white's uh knight on f3. So imagine
if these pieces are gone from the board.
That's a good thing to kind of do,
right? To visualize certain minor pieces
disappearing from the board. What effect
will that have on the position? Well, if
the knight on F3 disappears, then
clearly our control over the D4 square
only increases. And at that point, we
can seriously start contemplating
already putting a knight on D4, which
will be not quite unassalable. actually
quite far away from unassailable because
white can still use the dark squareed
bishop or even the C3 knight to trade
the knight off. But both of those moves
are associated with a lot of
awkwardness. And the best way to
threaten to trade the F3 knight is of
course to play the move D6, which again
also just improves our position and is a
normal developing move. But I like the
move D6 a little bit more than knight
F6. I actually think that we probably
should delay the move knight f6 until a
more opportune moment has occurred. And
as you'll see, we actually can develop
the knight to e7, which is very common
in the Sicilian. Okay. Now, we proceed
with our positional plan. We develop our
bishop to g4. We continue clamping down
on the d4 square. We trade a piece that
controls that square. This is like sort
of very classic positional chess 101.
Bishop B2. Now, what a lot of people
struggle with in a situation like this
is like, okay, do we actually
proactively take on F3 or is there no
hurry? So, it doesn't matter, right? You
can take on F3 or you can continue your
kingside development and both options
are good. We're going to try to
emphasize like classic rudimentary
positional play. So, I'm actually going
to eliminate this knight while we still
have a chance. The drawback of not doing
that is that the knight actually could
have moved away. And the trade of light
squareed bishops is okay for black, but
it's not quite as glamorous as getting
rid of white's knight. And again, I'm
going to repeat what I said earlier.
There is no hurry to put the knight on
d4. We can do it here. We can play
knight d4. And you can say, well, after
the trade, bishop takes d4, bishop takes
d4, we now have uncontested control of
all of the dark squares, right? Our dark
squared bishop is now operating
uncontested. That's a good thing. Knight
d4 is a solid move.
But we're going to practice restraint.
And what we're going to do instead is
find a developing square for the G8
knight such that it doesn't obstruct our
own control of the D4 square, which
would be the weakness of the move knight
to F6. So if we play knight F6 here,
later on we might then have to drop the
knight back down to D7, for example, to
increase our control over D4. But
instead, if you've played the Sicilian a
good amount, you should know that there
is what was introduced to me as the
botanic setup. And I think this has
several different names. The botanic
setup is how I was taught. Uh this is
the name that I was taught. And the
botanic setup simply entails fenettoing
your dark squareed bishop, then carving
out a alternate developing square for
the G8 knight with the move E6.
Specifically with the move E6 or E5.
Yeah. Uh the Babinik stuff is also E5.
So we play E6 and then we get this
knight out to E7. And the reason we do
all of this again is to make sure that
our dark court bishop is still unc is
unobstructed, right? We don't want our
knight blocking our bishop. Also, the
pawn on E6 is kind of an asset. It's
controlling some important squares. It's
controlling D5. It's controlling F5.
We're creating kind of a a toothy
construction in the center where our
pawns are are kind of like teeth, you
know, controlling all of these important
squares. Uh yeah, E5 I don't like. I
mean, E5 would be a very bad move here.
E5 would be a very bad move because it
would just return the favor, right? We
don't want to create a weakness of our
own on D5. Also, we don't necessarily
want to block in the bishop like that.
Okay, so now knight G7. Notice how
harmoniously our pieces are placed.
every piece is sort of clearly occupying
a well- definfined role and our general
strategy is to continue clamping down on
these center squares. Um, we're making
it very very hard for white to to
basically to move.
In earlier speedruns, I mentioned that
in the Sicilian, you want to avoid
playing E6 and G6 in the same breath.
This is a totally different scenario
because the center is closed. The caveat
to that rule is that when the center is
open, you often don't want to combine
the moves e6 and g6 because it creates
dark squared holes here. These holes are
totally inaccessible because white's got
a bunch of pawns in the center. So,
okay, like white can play a move like
knight b5 here. Big whoop. It's a total
paper tiger. Doesn't even threaten
anything. Just chase it away with a6.
That's also why when we play the move
E6, we shouldn't worry about quote
unquote weakening the D6 pawn because
the D6 pawn is well protected by the
queen and it's essentially unattackable.
Bishop G5 by our opponent. Okay, so I
I'm most definitely not afraid of white
taking on E7. That actually is what we
want. We want white to give away his
dark squared bishop especially for the
e7 knight which relatively speaking is
the the inferior the most inferior of
our pieces leaving the other knight to
jump into d4. So what I like here is to
sort of lure white you know to to prod
white into taking on e7 with the move
h6.
The reason I don't like the move castles
king side quite as much is because of
the move queen to d2 in response. And at
that point, white is already threatening
to trade the dark squareed bishops. And
I use the word threatening deliberately,
right? It is a serious positional
threat. We most certainly do not want to
get rid of our dark squareed bishop.
That is our the pride of our position.
So by playing H6, we are doing two
things. We are of course provoking our
opponent into taking on E7. But if white
drops back to H4, which is very likely,
doesn't happen, then we would be able to
castle kingside without fearing that
white's going to build up the battery
and trade bishops with bishop H6.
Hopefully that makes sense. So obviously
we take with the queen in order to leave
the knight, give the knight continued
access to to the D4 square. And we are
not worried about the king and the queen
being aligned once again because the
center is closed. Queen A4. Okay, the
knight is pinned. Our next move is
obvious. We need to complete our
development by castling king side. And
finally, we have exited the opening and
entered the middle game. Black is much
better. I wouldn't say that we're
winning. Probably if I had to throw out
an evaluation, I would say it's maybe
minus 1.5 minus 2, something like that.
So, it's a very serious advantage. And
and again, just notice the control that
we are exerting over the dark squares.
White cannot move. White is just totally
stuck. White is a bad bishop. And now,
we're going to start the process of
converting these sort of abstract
positional advantages into something
more concrete. I think this is what a
lot of people get anxious about. They're
like, "Well, yeah, I get it.
Hypothetically, you know, I get that
we're much better, but how do we
actually make something of these
positional advantages?" And this is, I
think, hopefully going to be the
instructive part of this game. So, of
course, there is the move knight D4,
which we can play now. We can play it a
little bit later. Let's let's set that
aside. Knight D4 is not a plan. Knight
D4 is a move. And if we play Knight D4
here, White's going to drop the bishop
back to D1. White's probably not going
to allow us to take on F3 and ruin the
pawn structure on the king's side. So if
you've played the Sicilian for a good
amount of time, there there is a a stock
plan in such positions that I think is
perfectly applicable here. And this plan
will probably involve the move knight D4
at some point. Essentially, the plan
consists in developing a queenside pawn
storm, but also to open up files on the
queen side. And when you are when your
pieces are placed in superior fashion
compared to your opponent's pieces,
usually opening up the center, opening
up flanks is going to benefit the side
with better placed pieces. What plan am
I talking about? What is this mysterious
plan that opens up files on the queen
side? Well, it's to prepare a very
particular kind of pawn break. And this
pawn break uh is involves the move B7
B5. That is the pawn break itself. And
to prepare it, to prepare it, we should
start with the move A6. very unassuming
looking move. A6. And if you look at
this situation tactically, you actually
might notice that B5 is given if things
remain as they stand. Now, B5 is
possible on the next move. We don't
actually even have to prepare it any
further. So, if you do some calculation
after B5, if white plays C takes B5, A
takes B5, queen takes B5, then the
knight can jump into D4. And not only
will we be able to take the bishop and
ruin the kingside pawn structure, but if
we want to be materialistic, we can jump
into C2. Notice that the moment a rook
appeared on E1, I'm already thinking
about landing a knight on C2, especially
because of how accessible that square is
through D4. Okay, so I'm combining
tactical observations and knowledge of
typical plans in this type of position.
And and this A6B5 plan is is virtually
universal in almost all anti-Sicilians.
And when I say anti-Scilians, I mean
nonopen Sicilians. Open Sicilian being
white uh playing the move knight f3 and
then d4. That's open Sicilian. Anything
else is considered basically
anti-icilians. So let's fast forward
again to the current position. We've
just played A6. Again, notice that I am
not rushing the move knight D4. I'm
keeping this for the most opportune
moment. H3. So, our opponent has not
actually taken any action against B5.
So, what's interesting is that we don't
have to play B5 immediately. I actually
like the thought of going knight D4
first. So, if you look at this situation
carefully, after knight D4, the bishop
really only has one square, right? D1.
Because if knight D4, bishop G4, we can
chase the bishop with H5. So after
knight d4, bishop d1, b5, the white
queen is virtually trapped. If you look
at that position carefully because it
can't go back to d1, there's now a
bishop there. C2 and b3 are protected by
the black knight. And if the queen traps
back to a3, then we push the pawn to b4.
That's another fork against the queen
and the knight. you could actually make
a serious case that B5 in this position
is a little bit inaccurate because it
allows the queen to drop all the way
back to D1. And in that situation, you
might say, "Oh, but then we play B4 and
we win the B2 pawn." But you don't quite
do that because B4, white has the move
knight A4 and white is still hanging on.
And after B5, queen D1, knight D4,
you're no longer threatening to ruin
white's structure with knight takes F3
check. So the effect of the move has
been slightly diminished. So hopefully
I've been able to explain my logic. Now
after knight D4, a very advanced player
would actually still play the move queen
to D1. I think this is white's only move
that doesn't lose almost on the spot.
But that is not an easy move to play
because that involves sort of
understanding why it's a bad idea to
move the bishop back, which to me seems
a lot more natural. If our opponent
plays queen D1, then we can respond with
B5. But it's totally worth starting with
this move. It's more flexible and to
test white's reaction. And that's not
called playing for tricks, right? That's
called being practical. If you if
there's no cost to you, then it's
absolutely worth playing the move order
that entails more tricks or that gives
your opponent more rope. But this is
this is a pretty minor subtlety. Both of
these moves would have been totally
fine. So, so you shouldn't think so
categorically about, oh, you know, if I
play B5, that means I made a big
mistake. No, both of these moves are
totally fine. We're talking about
relatively minor subtleties here. But
even if you're basically a beginner,
hopefully you were able to follow that
logic. And I I'll show this once again
after the game over the board for those
who had a little bit of a hard time
visualizing, which is also totally fine.
Yeah, rook E3 is possible, of course.
Rook E3 is possible, of course. But
then, first of all, we can still play
B5. And after rook E3, the sexy move
that we have is actually H5
with the idea of putting a bishop on H6
and chasing the rook away once again.
Bishop D1 is played and boom goes the
dynamite. We strike at the other side
with B5. And white is borderline I think
at this point already white is lost.
Okay. And now white is definitely lost
because the queen is literally trapped.
The queen is literally trapped. And
that's how quickly like at this level
when you know typical plans they tend to
work like a charm. I mean this was
pretty extreme. But it's not a
coincidence that this type of plan
resulted in success. Like if you
diligently learn and read about the
typical middle game plans and the
openings that you play and hopefully
this speedrun is going to actually help
you. If you want to follow my opening
recommendations, you want to build a
repertoire from scratch, hopefully I
will succeed in showing you these types
of typical plans that you can apply in
your own games. It's over. White has to
give the queen away for one for well the
most that white can give it away for is
the rook. Queen takes a technically the
best move, but in addition to the extra
queen, we have managed to keep all of
the advantages of the position to begin
with. So, it's completely lost. Now, of
course, um,
queen A5 here would be the only move to
keep the game going, but even after
queen A5, I think we could virtually
trap the queen
by playing, we'll talk about this after
the game, but I'm pretty sure B4 and
then maybe dropping the knight back to
C6 comes very close. We'll check. We'll
check. Queen A5. We can Okay, queen
takes A8 played. Rook takes a8
and
okay A3. Well, that's fine with us. We
can simply continue our plan. What was
our what was our plan? Well, our plan
was to expand on the queen side to open
up files. And the move here should occur
to you very naturally. Yeah, of course.
B4 is like literally begging to be
played especially because the white
rooks are disconnected which means a
takes B4 is impossible. Knight E2 is
good. Okay, so now again we have like a
gazillion ways to win this. I remind you
that in such cases there's two
overarching plans. The first is to aim
for simplification. The second is to use
the second is my preferred plan. you
don't really need to go out of your way
to simplify. If an opportunity to
simplify presents itself, then you
should take it, but you shouldn't
necessarily give away your advantages in
for the sake of simplification. This is
a great example. You know what I don't
like here? I don't like the idea of
playing B takes A3, rook takes A3, and
then trading the rooks. Like that is
unnecessary because our rook is better
than white's rook. Why are you trading?
Okay. So, in this case, I like a move
that keeps the tension. Now, what does
it mean to keep the tension? Well, what
do I see when I look at this? What I see
when I look at this is that our queen is
not really playing to its fullest
potential. Knight is good. The bishop is
good. The rook is good. Everything's
doing something. The queen is a little
bit kind of stuck in no man's land a
little bit. And I think about, okay,
well, where can the queen go? Well, we
can go to B7, for example, to skewer
X-ray the B2 pawn. Good. But I'm more
looking at white's king. And the moment
you look at white's king, as some of you
are suggesting, you're spotting the move
queen g5 with two ideas. Those with a
keen tactical eye should notice that
knight f3 check is now a threat, which
white doesn't defend against. We don't
need to say that twice. There's knight
f3. And the second idea, by the way, was
to infiltrate to d2. That wasn't the
only idea. If white had gone in this
position, knight E2 to G3, we would have
infiltrated to D2 with our queen,
forking the rook and the pawn on B2,
winning the game immediately.
But this ends it right away. This ends
it right away. And notice how quickly we
managed to win that. It was like boom
boom. Whereas if we had started to
simplify in this case and if we had
taken on A3 and then done all this other
stuff, the game would have been going a
lot longer. Knight takes C1. Obviously,
we take the rook. You know, again, very
important rule of converting material
advantages efficiently, right? At this
point, we're up a full queen. At this
point, simplification is almost always
justified, but still not really
necessary. And yet, I liked throwing in
B takes A3 just to clarify the situation
on the on the queen side. B takes A3.
Yeah, we can grab another pawn on G2.
That's a free pawn. But it's not just a
free pawn. and just look at what it does
to white's king side. So, this is a
no-brainer. You should definitely take
free stuff when it presents itself. And
a lot of people like don't keep that
straight in their mind. It's hard to
explain. There's no scientific formula
for like when do you at what point do I
continue taking material? When do I
instead go for simplification? In many
cases, when you're up like a queen,
there's like a gazillion ways to convert
and it's largely a matter of taste. So
here we should definitely not fear the
progress of the A pawn because the A
pawn is going absolutely nowhere. The
rook on A8 is stopping the pawn. You
don't even need to play rook A5. Even if
the white pawn reaches A7, we're just
going to pick that pawn off. So I like
bishop D4. That's a great move. But
we're just going to abide by our
strategy of taking free stuff. Just
let's just keep taking take on H3. If
permitted, we're going to take on D3. My
guess is that white's going to go bishop
C2 knowing players of this level, but
we'll see.
Okay, I was wrong. A5. And we can take
another pawn on D3. And incidentally, it
prevents A6.
Funnily enough, this also prevents A6.
So, one good thing to do if you're, you
know, not necessarily a beginner, but if
you're sort of entering intermediate
level, is to always question is to
always follow through with a question
when you're when you find yourself being
afraid of something, whether it's a past
pawn or some move. Never just take that
for granted. Always try to like figure
out exactly why you're afraid of this
thing and whether you should be afraid
of it. Queen drops back to C4, attacking
the rook, pressuring the bishop, keeping
contact with the knight. Yeah. Queen C4
is obvious without further comments. And
of course, thank you for the bishop.
Hopefully, white resigns here.
Hopefully, white resigns. Oh, I don't
know why Jeffrey's name is is on the
screen. That was hilarious. Yeah, it's
because Sorry about that. Wait, this
speedrun game is dedicated to Jeffrey,
my good friend. By the way, give him a
follow. And if you're watching on
YouTube, twitch.tv/gmjx.
He's awesome.
All right, let's quickly go over the
game. All right, so yeah, so C4, C4,
move two. This has been played against
me. And again, it's not such a bad move
if white follows it up accurately. If
white follows it up accurately. So after
knight C6, knight F3, let me just
quickly follow up on a comment that I
made about G6 technically not being the
best move. The reason it's not the best
move is because it allows white to
transition the game back into open
Sicilian channels. And obviously like
according to theory, white is better in
the marotzi bind. In this line, this is
what's most commonly recommended by
books. It's the moroti bind with the
pawns on c4 and e4. This position is
usually reached via the open move order.
Knight f3, knight c6, d4 immediately
accelerated dragon. And the marotzi bind
is defined by the move c2 to c4 as
opposed to knight c3 which is the
traditional accelerated dragon. And
after bishop G7, bishop B3, we won't
talk about this right now. We will, I'm
sure, have the Morozi probably even more
than once, but hopefully my logic makes
sense. Like I wouldn't mind getting this
here just to demonstrate typical ideas.
So that's why we uh we didn't play in
more topical fashion. If I was playing a
classical game, I'd probably play uh the
move I would probably play move E6.
Now the thing is if white plays d4 here
you actually get a bad version of the
maroti here I can get knight f6 in
already white's pawn center is under
very serious fire so the pawn on e4 is
hanging if knight c3 we can go bishop b4
and this is considered a pretty dubious
line for white and if white plays knight
takes c6 bc and e5 this is worth knowing
anytime you have the pawn on e5 the king
on e1 like this you should be thinking
about queen A5 check with a fork against
the pawn and the king. So I don't
remember what the books recommend here,
but it's probably not G6. Of course, our
opponent makes a serious positional
error. He plays D3, and this defines our
permanent domination over these key
central squares. Hopefully that makes
sense. Bishop G7. Let me just refresh to
get brighter colors. Knight C3. D6. So,
as we explained, we're going bishop G4
and getting rid of the knight in order
to increase and stabilize our control
over particularly the D4 square. But
we're not rushing with the move knight
D4. This is one of the the narratives of
this game is that we were patient. The
control over the square is much more
important than actually putting a piece
on the square. You have to keep those
two things separate in your mind, right?
Sometimes they're basically one and the
same, but a lot of time if you have a
piece controlling a square from a long
distance, you don't actually need to put
a piece on a square to assert your
dominance over that square. E6 the Bobik
setup putting the knight on E7 to not
obstruct the bishop's control over that
square. Isn't it bad taking on F3 if
it's not forced? Not at all. Not at all.
And you might say, well, I learned that
you shouldn't, you know, make two moves
with one piece and trade it for a piece
that's only made one move. And this is a
good example of where opening principles
are starting to get overtaken by
concrete considerations. Right? The
center is completely closed. And a lot
of principles and rules simply do not
apply when the center is closed. I
mentioned the fact of going E6 and G6.
When the center is closed,
virtually everything is on the table
because the center is often the only way
through which you can attack weaknesses.
When the center is closed, you don't
have to worry about anything a lot of
the time. And this is a great example of
that. So I think virtually every
speedrun I show you this very uh
memorable game from early in my career
where I played the moves E6 and G6, but
I played them when the center was open
and I got burned immediately. And I I
can't show this game enough. Let me show
it again. I ended up winning this game,
but that's totally beside the point.
super old game from 2005.
So, watch how quickly things go
downhill. He plays the Smith Moa. Plays
the Smith Moa.
Um, and I I take and I had no idea how
to play the Smith Moa at the time. So, I
I was kind of ad libing it. I played
knight C6. And at that point, I was
dabbling in the dragon. So, I decided
it's logical to play the move G6. So, he
plays bishop C4. Already G6 is
considered to be very dubious. So he
castles and now of course I had learned
about the bucknik setup. So I decided to
play e6 and I was like okay I'm going to
go knight e7 and I'm going to go castles
and I'm just going to be totally fine.
And I I did wasn't calculating at all.
Here the center is open which means the
df file is open which means that these
dark squares which are weakened
tremendously by the move e6 are now
easily exploitable by white's pieces.
And he immediately pounces. No knight
e5. E5 just gives away the pawn.
Although that is an idea worth
remembering to push E5 to solidify your
control over D6 here. This is not
necessary. Just straight away goes
knight B5
threatening an unstoppable check on D6.
But I decided I'm going to go knight F6
and knight D6 check is not as dangerous
as it seems. I can move my king and
black is still okay. But rather than
knight D6, he goes suddenly queen D6.
And I realize I'm busted on the spot
because there's literally no way to
prevent the fork on C7, which in this
case is going to win the queen. So all I
had to do was all I had left was the
move queen E7 check trade and he wins a
full rook on A8. As it turns out, things
were not so simple. I grabbed a pawn on
E4 and although white is completely
winning, I was later able to win the
knight on A8, getting compensation, and
I won the game. But the sort of gist of
this should be clear that with the open
center you should be very careful about
these two moves. When the center is
closed things the rules of engagement
are totally different because there is
no engagement between the armies.
So anyways that's a pretty long-winded
explanation but hopefully you're able to
understand what I'm getting at. Two
completely different types of positions.
So castles we go knight G7 bishop G5. We
played the move H6.
And the reason we played the move again
is because if we had castled instead,
this is a worth a worthwhile tool that
you should be familiar with even as a
beginner. This battery with the idea of
eliminating the fianeted bishop with
bishop H6. For example, let's make a
random move. But white plays bishop H6.
And of course, the point is that if you
move your bishop, you give up an entire
exchange. So you're virtually forced in
this case to acquies to the trade of
your main piece. Now if you have allowed
this the the traditional way that you
take the sting out of bishop H6 is you
preemptively move the rook. You
preemptively move the rook in order to
be able to drop the bishop back without
sacrificing the exchange. Sometimes
actually you can sacrifice the exchange.
So this would be fine, but it's a little
bit awkward to allow white's bishop to
sit on H6 like that. It's awkward and
it's totally unnecessary when we can
just throw in the move H6. And what this
does is it it takes the sting out of the
move queen D2. White can still play this
move, but this no longer threatens
anything.
Um, I could probably find an example
pretty quickly of sacking an exchange.
Yeah, just give me like 30 seconds.
So, this is an old Soviet game. Panov
against Semagen. Simagan was was a
grandmaster. He was very strong. Panov
of course is person after whom the Panov
attack in the Claron is named. He was an
IM. So this position occurs on the
board. This is a dragon Sicilian and in
the dragon this exchange sacrifice of
bishop H8 is very common actually. So
having as a student of these ideas you
might think that Samagen uh would play
rook E8 here so that you can meet bishop
H6 with bishop H8 but he feels that he
doesn't have time for that. He he needs
to get stuff going on the other side of
the board. So instead he goes rook C8.
Okay. Obviously Pan Panov goes bishop H6
and Sagen goes bishop H8. He feels that
the dark squared bishop in the dragon is
more valuable than that rook on F8. And
he is correct.
Panov grabs it. He takes back. And it's
not like black is winning on the spot or
anything, but watch how quickly his
decision to keep the bishop alive pays
off. First you go bishop c4. So the
position is very very oops sorry. The
position is very very unclear. It's not
like black is even better here. But
Samagan ends up crushing him. G5 knight
fd7. Bishop f1 to h3 by panov. Now
Samagen plays e6 in order to lock the
bishop out of the game and create kind
of again these like bumpers that control
a lot of the key central squares. Banov
goes king b1.
Knight centralizes to E5. And after F4,
Simagan finds a crazy idea. And this
idea directly justifies his decision to
keep the bishop on H6 alive.
Can anybody find it? I'm actually
curious. This is This is a nutty move.
And he was a very strong attacking
player.
This is a nutty move. And I'm not sure
it's sound. Yeah, knight f3 is correct.
He plays knight f3.
Knight takes F3 and now bishop takes C3.
Now he gives the bishop away, but for a
much better cause. Of course, the point
is if queen C3, you take on A2. Now the
line doesn't end here. After king A2,
rook C3 BC, white is a kingdom and a
horse for the queen. But it's
compensated by the fact that white's
white's king is incredibly weak and
white's pieces are poorly coordinated.
So for example, I think he was probably
intending the move queen C8 in order to
directly harass these incredibly weak
pawns. maybe prepare queen C4 check. My
guess is that black is doing quite fine
here without checking the engine. So of
course he plays BC and now D5.
That queen is heading directly for A3.
So Panov drops his own queen back to C1
to prevent him from coming to A3. But
now the knight jumps into the attack
with knight A4. It's like a classic
dragon attack. Ed and bishop takes A2
eliminating a key defender. King A1. He
doesn't take the bishop because if he
had taken the bishop, knight C3 and
queen B4, just look at the storm clouds
gathering around white's king. This is
just checkmate. And notice how safe
black's king is, right? Black's king is
totally out of the woods. Like it's just
a one-sided attack. So instead, he tries
to hide under the bishop, but the queen
still comes to C5. Then the knight drops
into C3. And black actually wins in
pretty simple fashion. He just plays
bishop takes C6. And in this position,
there is this overwhelming threat of
queen A5 and queen A2 with checkmate. So
Panov, seeing no other defenses, gives
up an entire rook to prevent that. But
now he's down, well, he's technically
only down, well, he's down two pawns,
but he's also getting mated and he loses
in just a couple of moves. Gets
checkmated.
Um, so maybe not the best example, but I
think you get kind of the point. This is
very, very common in the dragon.
exchange sacrifice with bishop H8.
King's Indian also happens. The sameish
variation. So back we go to our game.
Yeah. So that's about it.
Bishop takes C7 of course exacerbates
the situation. Now our domination has
reached just like epic magnitudes
because of just just the control that we
have over the game. And now after we
complete our development, we focus on
converting our sort of abstract
positional advantage into something
concrete. And of course, this plan of A6
and P5, which is so so common in
virtually all types of Sicilian
structures uh comes to the rescue here.
Um Joji Extend says, "What should white
do?" Well, white's I I wouldn't say that
white is helpless here, but it's it's
like borderline lost. So after a6, if I
was playing white here, I would probably
start by moving my queen out of the
danger zone. The queen on a4 actually
adds fuel to the fire because b5 comes
with tempo and the queen actually gets
trapped. So here probably we would have
played knight d4. And again, if I were
playing white, disclaimer, white's
position sucks. Maybe I would try to
play a4 to make it harder to play b5.
Um, maybe I would have played the move
G3 in order to create at least a
decently safe escape square for the
bishop. B5, bishop G2. And again, after
BC, DC, rook B8, that there's pressure
on the pawn, B3 runs into knight takes
B3, but white can survive. Rook B1, and
white holds on. Although, with this
knight sitting pretty on D4, it's going
to be very hard. How to find B5? Well, I
have no easy answer for that. You just
have to know it, right? I I don't think
I would be able to find a 65. That's a
little bit like asking, you know, how do
you know 9 * 7 is 63. It's it's almost
like memorizing the multiplication
tables. It's a hard plan to come up with
a priori. You you should just know that
it exists in anti-icilian structures and
you're like, well, how do I know it
exists? Well, you know, you read, you
you listen, and you focus on acquiring a
knowledge of of basic ideas. But it's
it's so common that I can literally just
show you a gazillion examples of that
plan being applied to the letter. Here's
a game of mine from a long time ago. Uh
that doesn't even start out with a
Sicilian, but quickly transposes into
one. And you can just see this plan in
action. So this was a Kings Indian
attack, but it kind of transposes into a
Sicilian
because I decided to play E4 C5. Knight
BD2, Knight C6. So watch what happens.
First, I do exactly what I did in the
game. Rook B8, A4, Bishop G4. So, trade
the light squared bishop because the
light squared bishop is the least
integral piece in black's camp. Now, we
drop the knight back to D7, which is I
mentioned this move in our speedrun
game. It's just that we decided to put
our knight on E7 to begin with. Same
idea. We want the bishop to occupy the
entire diagonal. And after knight D2,
guess what I played? You might say, I
played B5. Not yet. Don't play B5 here
because that allows A takes B5 and then
it gives white a really nice C4 square.
Yeah, you've opened the B file, but you
have now a bunch of weaknesses on the
queen side. You have to be more patient
than that. A6. You want to attack with
the pawns. F4. B5. A A B C3. Trying to
blunt the diagonal. B4. Again, using the
pawns to carve and break through. And if
white would have played C4 here, it
would have been a very similar scenario
to the game. Of course, my opponent
didn't. He's strong. He tried to mix
things up with E5, but in the end I
pretty easily parried all the threats
and I ended up uh I ended up I ended up
winning the pawn. Like at the end of the
day, he ended up losing this big pawn on
C3 and I won the game in the end. So I
can show you a thousand examples of this
B5 plan. But for now, suffice it to say
that you should just this should be the
first thing you enter into your database
of ideas if you want to play the
Sicilian properly.
Um, okay. Let's go back to speedrun game
one more time. And once that plan is set
in motion, white is in huge trouble. H3,
knight D4. Again, I would play queen D1
here. I think this might be the last
chance after bishop D1 B5. Yeah, the
game is over because if white would have
played queen A5. First of all, if queen
A3, then of course B4 traps forks forks
the the queen of the knight. So, queen
A5 was the last hope.
And here, I think the simplest is just
to play rook F to B8. First, we defend
the B6 square,
right? If you play knight C6
immediately, then white plays queen B6.
So, anytime you have a situation like
this, right, where the queen basically
has only one escape square. You should
start by asking yourself, well, do I
actually need to rush? Do I need to make
a move that carries a direct threat or
can I make a second order threat? A
second order threat is a move that car
that threatens a threat, right? Rook FB8
itself is not a threat. Knight C6 is the
actual threat, but rook F8 sets it up
and knight C6 is going to win the game.
And white can do nothing about knight
C6. Nothing about knight C6.
Um if okay, I guess there's the move
knight E2 to open up a pathway for
white's queen. Who can tell me what
black should do against knight E2? And
this is all about being flexible, right?
Yeah, knight C6 was the idea just now,
but you're asking yourself, okay, but
what else can I do in this position?
Make the silk go. Not B4. I knew some
people would fall for this move. It's
tempting, but after queen A4, the queen
is surprisingly safe, right? What are
you going to attack the queen with?
Instead, you actually play it even
simpler. BC. The B2 pawn is hanging and
white loses it. And with that B2 pawn
goes white's entire queen side. the
position just white can resign here. I
mean, just look at this. Takes takes.
You're attacking F2. Your bishop is now
a monster. White can't even play rook E2
because now you take and the rook anyone
hangs. White can't play bishop E2
because again if rook takes E2. So it is
just totally lost. Totally lost.
Um so there is nothing that white could
do after B5. Of course after the trade
the queen is literally trapped. We win
the queen. We push B4. We activate our
queen, right? We just identify which
piece isn't playing to its fullest
potential. And of course, the idea was
to infiltrate the D2 square after knight
F3. The rest is obvious without
comments. We just ended up taking all of
white's pawns.
And that's that's all she wrote, folks.
So, this actually ended up being a
pretty extensive analysis. Um, which
means I probably will put this out as
its own YouTube video. This was
instructive. I think this was our first
like toptobottom instructive game that
wasn't decided by an opening blunder.
Um, so I hope you enjoyed it. I hope you
enjoyed the examples. And uh, again, our
our emphasis is on openings and on
building your knowledge of opening
ideas. So, it's entirely acceptable to
not play the openings I recommend in the
speeder. I still hope you'll find the
games instructive, but I'm doing this
with an aim toward helping relative
beginners basically start their opening
acquisition of opening repertoire from
from scratch. So, the one thing the
funny thing is the one thing I haven't
fully decided is whether I'm
recommending Smith Moa or Alip and
Sicilian. I think since the openings are
so similar to each other, I might
alternate them.
Where can we find Accelerated Dragon
Theory? Well,
there are books on the accelerated
dragon. I don't actually have any of
them. I know they exist, but again, this
is not going to be a satisfying
question, but I hope that through the
course of the speedrun, that's my
vision. My vision is that you like by
watching all of the games, you will
actually be able to construct a full
repertoire for yourself. We will
eventually get games where our opponents
go into the main lines and that's where
we will discuss theory and eventually I
might put some of the theory into lie
studies. I haven't decided yet but uh
you know let let's not jump the gun just
yet.
How should black deal with the mori
blind? Okay. So again
please understand the order here. We
will face the maroti blind eventually.
When we do, I will talk about it very
extensively.
And actually, my recommendation against
the Morozi is going to be not bishop G7,
but straight away to play the move
knight F6, attacking E4.
A lot of people here already are going
to play takes on E5. This is like the
first trap. But that's not the reason
I'm recommending this line. Here you
have queen A5 check. The point of knight
F6 is after knight C3, you take on D4.
And then you play D6. This is a very
underrated line in my opinion. And this
is a very dangerous line for white. The
point is simple. You're luring the queen
to D4 so that after bishop G7, there is
a pin going on and you're trying to
force white to lose more tempe, moving
the queen back from D4. And this is a
very dynamic line. Tons of players with
white end up misplaying this super
quickly. We will get this, I'm sure,
probably sooner rather than later.
But anyways, let's put that aside for
now. Thanks for hanging out today and
I'll see you all tomorrow.
[Music]